[Music]
great so ethereum in uh 30 minutes so
this is a a presentation that I've given
at I think basically every single Devcon
since launch though I think what's
interesting is how as uh ethereum the
ecosystem uh changes and as ethereum the
protocol changes as the times change uh
the contents also end up changing quite
a bit right so if you go back to the
equivalent of this from 2015 you'll hear
a lot about Uncle blocks of course Uncle
blocks are a feature of proof of work
that we have proof of stake and so we
don't have Uncle blocks anymore now
ethereum also uh of course uh now has a
layer twos and back in
this would not contain layer 2s at all
and now of course as we know layer 2s
are half the story right so ethereum is
above all an evolving ecosystem and uh
the contents of this are going to keep
changing as the technology changes and
also as the emphasis of the uh ecosystem
changes from building basic
infrastructure uh to now also really
putting a huge amount of focus on the
applications so what is ethereum so
first ethereum is the world computer so
who here remembers etherium being the
world
computer this is the place where I'm
supposed to like put that Meme the where
like there's the guy with the gun in
space saying always has been but I don't
know I never understood why you're why
like like giving someone such an amazing
and beautiful Revelation is supposed to
come at the same time as uh shooting
them in space 20,000 km away from home
and so you I'm not going to do that
today so ethereum is the world computer
it always has been always will be uh so
in addition to this ethereum is an
incredibly large and diverse onchain
economy um and uh
fortunately know Josh uh right before uh
well one one skipped before me made an
incredibly good presentation talking
about all of the different aspects of
the economy and also so ethereum is an
incredibly large and diverse Global
community and I and Josh and the uh
automated like intro thing before that I
think did a a really good job of showing
that too so ethereum is many things
right I think uh they're like also Pro
probably you're supposed to like put up
a flashing sign saying e is money as
well but you know ethereum is a lot of
things right and if ethereum is all of
these different things at the same time
so how does the world computer work
right so the way that I think about this
is uh you layer one is the Shust machine
and Layer Two is uh the GPU right so the
layer one of ethereum that is the core
ethereum blockchain this is the anchor
that keeps the rest of the ecosystem
safe and holds the rest of the ecosystem
together layer one is the reason why
layer twos are able to trustly talk to
each other and at least once everything
upgrades to stage two you will be able
to take an asset issue it on optimism
and then move it and hold it inside of a
smart contract on arbitrum and do so
with zero counterparty risk layer one is
not there to be ultra fast it is not
there to do a million transactions per
second layer one is first and foremost
there to be decentralized to be robust
and to be something that is Dependable
Layer Two is the GBU so Layer Two is uh
all of you uh in the in the room who are
part of any single layer two um who here
is part of a layer
two yay who here has used the layer
two who here has used layer
one good it's uh we're all users here so
actually know there's lots of these
different gpus right and ethereum of the
world computer is able to hold together
because each and every one of these gpus
is connected to the trest machine
through optimistic uh proof systems zero
knowledge proofs snarks Starks Bas jolts
plun plunk you know whatever the buzz
words are right uh and uh that all of
these systems actually ensure that ler
one is able to trustly verify what is
going on inside of the layer tws and
layer twos also are able to trustly uh
read what is happening on layer one so
there's an important interplay between
these two components and together they
make up the ethereum that is here today
so what is the L1 it's a chain it runs
proof of stake it doesn't Afra
so it's so what does this me right so
ethere one is uh a chain that has uh
existed alt together for um more than n
years now and it's existed in its
current proof of stake form for um a
little bit over two years and I think
one of the really important things for a
Bas layer to have is you want to have
clear evidence that that you're building
on a base layer that is decentralized
that is open that is robust and that is
likely to keep those traits going
forward into the future right and one
one part of that of course is so like
something that is slow to change right
one part of that is being something that
is not suddenly going to wake up on a
Tuesday have new management and then
suddenly decide that it's just like
totally going to like start deleting a
whole bunch of applications change its
entire model and do other push the fees
up by a factor of 10 and do other things
without warning another part of
decentralization and resilience is
actually recovery right so whenever
problem actually starts to arise
actually be able to recover from it and
have some way of actually improving the
qualities of the layer one over time so
over here um this is uh on the left a
chart of Bitcoin proof of work um mining
pools and on the chart if uh on the
right if they in proof of stake mining
pools actually um I'm deliberately being
generous here because uh putting Bitcoin
proof of work mining pools because
before the merge actually ethereum proof
of work decentral uh was even more
concentrated than this right and so what
we see here on the right is you see
actually a pretty diverse different set
of staking pools and if you zoom into
either of the top items on the uh chart
on the top left so Lio and it has
somewhere somewhere a little bit under
30% but then actually Lio is like it's
not one actor right it's a dow
technically the deposits are split
between 40 different node operators
approximately and there's some more
complicated structure that keeps
updating uh but it's so I think it's
reasonable to think of it as being like
somewhere between one actor and 40
actors exactly where like this is like a
problem for you social science people to
figure out right how do you actually
quantify the decentralization thing
there are there there's even grant
opportunities for this stuff so that's
uh like so that's number one right and
then number two unidentified now
unidentified is not an actor just like
there's no the any key on your keyboard
is not actually a key so unidentified
like we actually don't know what it is
there's probably lots of solo stakers
lots of small business stakers lots of
uh various tiny staking pools also not
one actor right so ethereum L1 today
actually has a surprisingly High degree
of decentralization in its proof of
stake design and this is a property that
I think has only gotten better over
time here is one thing one property that
actually has gotten a lot better so
ethereum uh about uh 5 years ago was
basically just gu right and when you
have an ecosystem that is dominated by
one client that itself becomes a central
point of failure right so who here
remembers the 2016 dos
attacks
yay so you know remember wake up 5:17
a.m. get a military style wakeup call um
you know say Hey you have to go down to
you know like the thing that we suddenly
turned into a war room now go down and
then oh someone discovered a bug in the
clients now the entire chain is stopped
and then we fix it and then two 3 days
later the the some guy somewhere finds
another bug and then 3 Days Later
another bug and then that keeps going on
for a whole month until eventually uh we
have to hard Fork but during that period
actually the ability for ethereum to
have two different clients at the time
they were gu and parody basically saved
the chain there were like there were
times when there was a bug that would
hit gu but not parody there were times
when there was a bug that would hit
parody but not gu um and uh so ethereum
actually gained a lot from having
multiple software implementations and
this is something that as of 2024 is
probably at the best that it's ever been
in ethereum's history
so so on the left you have consensus
clients consensus clients handle the
proof of stake part of ethereum on the
right you have execution clients
execution clients handle the evm part of
ethereum so as we we can see the single
client with the highest market share is
gu which is like somewhere around 50%
and actually this is uh from a source
that's basically assuming that most
unidentified clients are gu and so it
could easily be below 50% right so let's
say it's about 50 so what happens if
there is a bug in any ethereum client
like literally today right now okay
anyone here has like a
bug okay uh Josh can you check as
ethereum still running
I'm going to guess it is um you know bet
like 99.99% Plus on poly Market okay
so what so case one what happens if the
client is gu that's the worst case if
the client is gu and there's a bug what
realistically happens basically chain
splits in half one half follows gu one
half follows the other clients but on
both sides the chain stops finalizing to
finalize you need 23 if you have less
than 23 the chain keeps blocks keep
getting created but the chain stop
finalizing and so if you are a user an
application a business and you're
waiting for confirmation on some
transaction you're you're probably
actually going to be waiting for a
finality and so if the chain splits in
half because of a client bug well
actually your neither chain is going to
finalize and so you're going to detect
that and you're going to be on standby
what's realistically going to happen
cord davs get on high alert figure out
which client actually has the bug and
the bug gets fixed the one time this
happened in ethereum actually yeah fun
fact I actually set the transaction that
did it myself this was back in 2016 uh
basically everything was fixed within 12
hours so that's the worst case every
other case basically if prism and
Lighthouse have a bug all that happens
is that ethereum stops finalizing for
like about a day at most and then it B
it just goes back to normal any other
client you're you're not going to notice
anything at all so in terms of practical
decentralization having multiple clients
is extremely helpful and also having
multiple clients is extremely helpful
because it diversifies the power and the
control over the uh eorum ecosystem
especially in any kind of contentious
situation right if some kind of Dow Fork
type incident happened again and one
particular development team made a
choice is unpopular then even if that
one uh that one development team just
insists on pushing it through users are
going to be very easily able to just
switch to the other clients and just
completely route around them this is not
something that is anywhere close to that
practical in a single client ecosystem
having a diverse multi client ecosystem
is actually very difficult to achieve I
think aside from ethereum no other chain
has really gotten to achieved anything
close to this and even outside of
ethereum like even web browsers web
browsers supposed to be an open standard
reality is like something like 80% of
the pl plus of the ecosystem probably
even more runs on some Fork of webkit
and the rest runs on Firefox which is
kind of valant trying to hold its own as
an alternative and uh is uh doing pretty
well it's one of the browsers that I use
but like you can see right like there
there there are natural pressures toward
um you know homogenization and toward
one implementation winning and ethereum
actually has managed to Buck this trend
so in ethereum um two years ago this
chart was worse and so ethereum's uh
decentralization is not only able to not
get worse but it's also able to actively
respond to problems that exist and over
time push to make them better if you
building an application that you needed
to exist 5 years from now 10 years from
now and that you want to be robust and
continue working five or 10 years from
now the what properties do you want the
chain you're building on to have I think
properties like these are exactly what
you would be looking
for with 32 eth or with less than 32 eth
if you join a pool there's more and more
really interesting pool options that are
appearing um there's even you know
things like oall Squad staking like the
there's options around
okay um there's options around like
basically creating smaller pools with
your friends there's different pools
that follow all kinds of different rules
and so there's lots of different ways
for you to become a Staker and if you're
a Staker then you become part of this
network of nodes that is securing the
ethereum blockchain so earn rewards
while securing ethereum so know I guess
uh this is know how the foundation
propaganda describes that it has a cute
elephant uh so good cheers for the
elephant uh so you know you two can join
the network and you two can help secure
it so also even if you're not a Staker
you can also run an ethereum node and
you could verify the chain
so this is uh a computer I mean I guess
these days nobody even has desktops that
look like this right it's like you
either have laptops or you have like
some crazy like GPU construction that's
like basically like looks almost like a
server right but like I don't know I
mean I just like shoved like a desktop
computer into stable diffusion 3.5 and
it like put this out so that's the
computer you get uh but uh you know you
can run an ethereum node on your
computer and you can verify the ethereum
chain right so this is really important
because if you have users that are
verifying the chain then even a majority
of the stakers acting together even two3
of the stakers acting together are not
able to change the rules on people
without everything breaking right
there's the ethereum rules they can only
change
through a hardk that is agreed upon
through wide Community consensus they
cannot be pushed through by a majority
or super majority of the stakers and
this is something that is really key and
really important and makes blockchains
very different from almost any other
kind of protocol and I think this is one
of those things that's really valuable
and really important to preserve I
think even among blockchain ecosystems
it's basically Bitcoin and eum that
really have a strong um culture of like
really at least among the large ones
right of of of actually trying to make
it possible and keep improving people's
ability to verify the chain and there's
a lot of protocol upgrades that are
coming that precisely have the goal of
making it even easier to verify the
chain so today um you have this uh
tomorrow uh you will uh be able be able
to one run node without requiring more
than a small amount of storage using
stateless clients so this is uh in my
big like series of six posts this is
going to be the one on the verge right
so stateless clients is a very important
section light clients uh so there's a
project called Helios which is doing a
form of light verification of the chain
so light verification is not perfect it
still follows the consensus and so if
51% of nodes change the rules you are
going to follow them but but it does
mean that if you're using a light client
that you do not have to trust an RPC
node to tell you any kind of information
about the chain and so Helios is uh
building a light client for ethereum
that does verification of the proof of
stake part of uh ethereum and uh also
actually starting to build light clients
for l2s um as well the longer term
future of course is we want to snark the
whole chain and once we snark the whole
chain you will be able to verify the
ethereum rules on extremely large or
extremely tiny Hardware so node writing
requirements and pushing those down is a
key part of the ethereum road map going
forward also uh staking with with less
eth this is one of those very active
research requirements right so 32 eth
it's still high and uh you know it's
even higher than it was two weeks ago
but my my okay
[Applause]
but you know my think like I would like
for people to be stakers with one e and
so I think there's a different ways to
do this there is orbit there is uh just
making a large number of aggregation
improvements but there's a lot of
protocol improvements that are coming
specifically in order to make staking
easier and more accessible and to make
running a node that verifies the chain
easier and more accessible so what runs
on the ethereum L1 so some high value
application use cases so a lot of high
value defi runs on L1 um ens is uh
currently on L1 though it's uh
increasingly doing doing more and more
with uh layer twos then uh a lot of
uh diff various applications um all kind
just all kinds of things in every
category uh people just hold assets on
layer one so lots of high value
application use cases on layer one also
managing block rots and and state roots
and proof systems for layer twos layer
one is the thing that secures layer 2os
cross layer two operations um and layer
one needs to still be powerful enough to
handle cross um a lot of things
happening especially in the case where a
layer two fails the difference between a
layer two and an independent chain is
that even if your warer 2 gets 51%
attacked or 91% attacked or the team
shots down layer one is still stands
there to protect the users users are
able to prove their whole their assets
and their ownership and their state
inside of the layer two and migrated
down back down to layer one in order for
this to actually be possible layer one
needs to actually be powerful enough to
handle the load if a layer two actually
does fail recently there was a live
experiment of this uh so dyd DX V3 I
believe shut down recently and the uh L2
beat people actually wrote their own
implementation of escape hatch software
and so without any involvement from the
dydx team uh users are able to take any
assets that they have ins um inside of D
ydx V3 and bring it back down to the
ethereum L1
so layer twos are not just multi the
ability to Mo move your assets out of
the layer two and back to layer one if
the layer 2 fails without the layer two
teams involvement is not just Theory it
is
reality
so okay L1 runs some applications and L1
protects the l2s what do the l2s do l2s
provide speed and scale so on the left
here you have a chart of like basically
the same as the chart that Josh showed
earlier basically Layer Two fees and
this is just what they've done this year
so this year Layer Two fees have gone
down from about 50 cents to less than 1
cent so this is a massive change right
this basically means that for an
incredibly wide class of applications
ethereum has overnight gone from
being basically unaffordable to being
completely affordable so that's fees
[Applause]
now transaction inclusion times right so
who here remembers the experience of
sending a transaction and then having to
wait some arbitrary number of minutes
could be 10 could be 40 could be 90 for
the transaction to get
included who here remembers having this
experience in
ethereum who here remembers having this
experience in ethereum in the past 6
months so ethereum has improved
massively now this is actually a pretty
linear progression that we've had all
the way since the beginning right so
Bitcoin 10minute block times and uh
Bitcoin has uh this uh thing called A
Plus un distribution that of course
ethereum also had um had during the
proof of work era but then we decided we
don't like fish and so we switched to
proof of steak
so Bitcoin average walk time 10 minutes
often you have to wait up to 1 hour now
in in ethereum uh the average block time
is 12 seconds but then there's still
this like annoying phenomenon where if
you send a transaction and you get
unlucky with the gas price that you set
maybe you would have to wait like 10
minutes or 20 minutes accidentally EIP
1559 which came in 2021 basically solved
that and created a situation where
you're able to reliably send a
transaction and expect to see it
included usually within one block and
then the merge because of this
interesting Quirk of mathematics
even though the average time between
blocks reduced only from 13 seconds to
12 seconds the average time between you
sending a transaction and your and your
transaction getting included in a block
reduced from a little bit more than 13
seconds to a little bit more than six
seconds um so math problem figure out
why this is true it's actually a really
fun fact so post merge basically goes
down to like about 6 to 30 seconds and
then finally with layer twos you have
preon
and you have layer twos that are fast
enough to just confirm your transaction
within a couple hundred
milliseconds so layer twos provide speed
layer twos provide scale and the way
that you as a user see scale is you get
to be part of an application where lots
and lots of things are happening and at
the same time your transaction fees get
to continue to be
cheap so history of ethereum right so
November 2013 the white paper July 2015
the launch around 2018 that was the time
when ethereum settled on it's
approximate design for proof of stake
and data availability sampling so the
original papers and like documents for
data availability sampling and aaser
coding um I wrote those back in 2017 and
then we settled on uh the Casper the
Friendly finality Gadget also at the end
of
2017 actually if you really want and you
can dig I think it's like either GitHub
ethereum research or like GitHub
ethereum simple Casper you just like
search for the directory called Simple
Casper and you can find like contracts
written in serpent like who here
remember
serpent okay who here uses serpent good
I mean I mean I think like I think
python is uh like is really beautiful
but I think if you uh like if you want
that then you should code in Viper Viper
is actually like great it's actually
kept improving quite a bit for the last
couple of years so we had basically yeah
okay yay glad for Viper um
okay and so in 2017 actually we
attempted to like basically do this like
full like abstraction thing and even
write the proof of stake logic directly
as a smart contract and so there's this
like really fun demo that we launched at
I think it was actually like 2320
Bangkok time on December 31st 2017 and
like you know we wanted to get something
out before New Year's but then like the
demo
it ended up like breaking up pretty
quickly you know it was early days but
since then of course it's not early days
anymore and at the start of 2018 a
really massive effort started to
actually build out the ethereum proof of
St system and to build out the ethereum
scaling system which has since then
turned into the blobs that we have today
2022 the merge switching from proof of
work to proof of steak
2024 The Surge part one right so if you
look into the road map diagram and you
look into the search section you see
that there's two Milestones there's one
that I call Basic rollup scaling and
there's one that I call full rollup
scaling and basic rollup scaling
basically says you need major ler 2os to
hit stage one and you need blobs to
exist and so 2024 we actually hit that
the next step is having actual like
fully running data availability sampling
and major ear 2 is hitting stage two so
I think that will happen and I think
that will happen sooner than people
and it's up to the ler 2 teams to build
this future of ethereum there are still
a lot of problems that are left to solve
so we want upgrades to decentralization
who here wantsum to be
decentralized who here wants ethereum to
be
centralized okay okay so one person
wants ethereum to be
centralized okay um censorship
resistance wants to censor
ethereum okay a couple more hands um
Quantum resistance who here wants
ethereum to break the first time a Quant
of computer comes
out okay one hand that's good you know
maybe it's like you know you know
sometimes like you need collapse in
order for Renewal to happen right so
further upgrades to make sure that
decentralization sensorship resistance
and Quantum resistance continue
happening Progressive upgrades to
efficiency and scale um so so Layer Two
I think is going to scale extremely
quickly and its safety is going to
improve quickly over the next few years
and also I expect Progressive upgrades
cautious upgrades but still Progressive
and definitely ongoing upgrades to layer
one capacity in different forms as well
over the over the next years and I think
one of the big reasons why we need to do
this one is to support the activity that
continues to happen on layer one itself
and two because ultimately if something
breaks on a layer two layer one still
needs to be there to be as a back stop
and so the maximum theoretical safe
capacity of l2s is proportional to to
the capacity of L1 we're going to have
upgrades to data availability sampling
to increase the number of blobs that
ethereum can support as of about a week
ago ethereum is actually hit price
discovery mode meaning the uh in terms
of blobs meaning that the number of
blobs that is actually being us being
used on ethereum exactly equals the
protocol that long-term Target now we
need to scale this number upgrades are
happening to actually do this so
upgrades to data availability sampling
we've now we have also scaled enough
that a wide variety of applications are
possible ens consumer payments social
one category that I think is going to be
extremely important over the next decade
is mixed financial and non-financial
applications applications that make use
of the power of Finance But ultimately
to serve ends that go be that go beyond
financial goals and I think there's lots
of very powerful applications here and I
think it's uh we've spent a long time
making the technology better and we will
continue doing this but it is at the
level where now is the time to build
thank you
[Applause]